Chitral Puthran

Data Scientist | Google Analytics Certified

Career Summary

A proficient **Python Programmer**, specializing in **Machine Learning, Data Visualization, and Data Preprocessing**, with internship experience at **Nokia Bell Labs** in Data Science, and an **active learner**. A **Graduate Research Assistant** in Machine Learning and Big Data, with a **Master of Science Degree in Computer Science** from the University of New Haven, 2019. A **Google Analytics Certified Individual**, 2019.

Work Experience

Graduate Research Assistant

2017-09 - Present

University of New Haven

- Examined various online media streaming business models, aggregated data about user ratings for movies from heterogeneous sources and forecasted ratings based on a prediction model, in a Recommender System, with the help of Python 3.6 and Apache Spark 2.2.0.
- Developed a Tweepy Streaming Engine to collect live tweets about natural disaster situations and implemented a context filtering model to classify tweet with relevant, valuable information for disaster relief organizations and first responders.
- Program Files and Report.

Data Science and Machine Learning Intern

2018-06 - 2018-08

Nokia Bell Labs

- Assisted the research led by Dr. Abdol Saleh at Bell Labs Consulting, by programming Jupyter Notebooks for data extraction using APIs in Python with learning instructions and reproducible code snippets.
- Successfully collected time-series data from 1960 to 2017, for 140
 macroeconomic indicators for 195 countries from The World
 Bank and International Labour Organization, and 256 macroeconomic indicators
 for 40 countries from Organisation for Economic Co-operation and
 Development through APIs using Python, aggregated in 2 million+ data points.
- Program Files and Report.

Relevant Projects

Amazon Alexa Reviews

Independent Work

- Implemented a customized Random Forest and Gradient Boosting Classifier using scikit-learn in Python.
- Cleaned, analyzed and summarized insights product reviews with the help of NumPy, Pandas and curated graphs in Matplotlib and seaborn.
- GitHub repository.

Skills

- Python
- NumPy, Pandas
- · Matplotlib, Seaborn, Plotly
- Scikit-learn, Keras, SHAP, lime
- Machine Learning
- Data Visualization, Data Cleaning
- SQL, MySQL
- SpaCy, NLTK
- Object-Oriented Programming (OOP) with Python.
- Git
- Google Analytics

Certifications

- Google Analytics Individual Oualification - 2019
- Microsoft Technology Associate -2017

Scholarship

Experiential Graduate
 Assistantship Program (EGAP) with
 75% tuition fee assistance.

Completed Courses

- Machine Learning by Stanford University on Coursera
- Machine Learning A-Z[™]: Hands-On Python & R in Data Science
- Statistics for Business Analytics A-Z™
- Learning Git and GitHub
- Interactive Python Dashboards with Plotly and Dash
- Python for Data Science Tips, Tricks, & Techniques
- Building Deep Learning Applications with Keras 2.0
- Advanced SQL for Data Scientists
- Amazon Web Services Machine Learning Essential Training

Mobile Description Web Application

Independent Work

- Extracted and Transformed mobile device descriptions such as model, CPU, dimensions, release date with Python using FonoApi, NumPy, Pandas, and MySQL
- Developed a web application with Java Server Pages, Bootstrap and Apache Tomcat.
- GitHub repository.

Education

Master of Science in Computer Science

2017 - 2018

University of New Haven

Coursework: Python Scripting, Java Programming, Distributed Databases, Advanced Python in Data Science, Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning, Web Database Application Development, Database Systems

Bachelor of Engineering in Computer Engineering

2013 - 2017

University of Mumbai

Relevant Courses: Distributed Database. Structured Programming Approach, Object-Oriented Programming Methodology, Data Structures, Database Management System, Analysis of Algorithms

Online Conference

AWS Innovate: Build AI-Enabled Applications and Train 2019-03-05 Models

Amazon Web Services (AWS)

Attended Tracks:

- Get Started with Amazon SageMaker: Build, Train, and Deploy Machine Learning Models in the Cloud.
- Remove Your Biggest Challenge to Getting Started with ML: Using Amazon SageMaker Ground Truth to Label Data at 70% Less Cost
- Integrate Amazon.com's ML Techniques for Customer Recommendations and Forecasting Workflows into Your Applications